A Guide to the Smith Family Papers 1965.0001
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
Smith Family Papers
1774-1981
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1965.0001
7.75 Linear Feet
The Smith family of Canterbury, CT, owned and operated a number of mills in the section of Hanover from the mid-eighteenth century until the 1940s. The original site on Little River, north of Hanover and Woodchuck Hill Roads, became the home to five successive generations of Smiths.
Biography
The Smith family of Canterbury, CT, owned and operated a number of mills in the section of Hanover from the mid-eighteenth century until the 1940s. The original site on Little River, north of Hanover and Woodchuck Hill Roads, became the home to five successive generations of Smiths.
The earliest record of the family in Canterbury can be traced to the mid-eighteenth century when Eliezer Smith (1737-1813) owned and possibly established a sawmill and carding mill at the location on Little River. At the time of his death in 1813, ownership of the mills was transferred to his son Eleazer (?-1843).
At the time of Eleazer's death in 1843, his land was divided among his seven children and his widow, Elipha. One half of the mill property was bequeathed to Elipha, and one half was put up for sale to pay for a creditor's charge ($985.55). In 1844, Eleazer's son, Eleazer (1797-1882) bought the property for $990.00 and was given control of Elipha's property as well. Details of the property divisions and sales can be found in the Canterbury Probate records at the Canterbury Town Hall.
According to Allen Lincoln's History of Windham County, five mills were in operation at this time; a carding and spinning mill, a second mill, which ran a picking machine, a grist mill, a saw mill and a shingle mill.
In 1882, at the time of Eleazer's death, all five mills were transferred to his son Lester (1842-1898). Shortly after, several of the mills were destroyed by fire, but were soon rebuilt in addition to a new grain mill. When Lester died in 1898, the ownership was transferred for the final time to his son, Frank. The mills remained in operation until the 1940s, around which time they fell into disrepair and were abandoned.
The remains of the mill have been left at the site, which has since become overgrown and is accessible only by foot. The rocks of the dam, the head and tailraces, and the main shaft from the turbine are all clearly evident. Also, the Smith home, built in the eighteenth century, remains, and is being restored by its present owners.
A close relationship between the Allen and Smith families is evident from the papers. Apparently, this friendship was encouraged by two factors: the Allens owned nearby woolen mills and fostered a business tie and Lester Smith married Imogene Allen in the 1860s.
[Sources: Canterbury Town Hall: Probate and Tax assessor Records. Connecticut State Library: Barbour Collection, Census records, church records, family and Bible records, Headstone inscriptions and probate records. Allen B. Lincoln, A Modern History of Windham County: A Windham County Treasure Book. Chicago: S.J. Clarke Publishing Company, 1920.]
Scope and Content
The papers include correspondence, both business and personal, business and financial records, ledgers, account books, daybooks, and printed materials collected by the family.
Arrangement
The Papers are divided into two series.
Series I: Family papers (undated, 1790-1923) contain papers and records of the family members and those persons with whom they corresponded. The papers are arranged alphabetically by name and further divided by the type of material in chronological order. The major portion of the series includes the papers of seven members of the Smith family and five members of the Allen family, related to the Smiths by marriage. Papers of personal friends and business associates of the two families comprise a small portion of the series. Unidentifiable company records and family correspondence are located in Box 8.
Because of the difficulty of distinguishing precisely between the papers of the two Eleazer Smiths, all records dated before the 1843 death of the elder Eleazer have been presumed to be his. All records after 1843 have been associated with the younger Eleazer (1797-1882). It is possible, therefore, that some of the early papers of the son may have been placed with those of his father.
The major types and their inclusive dates are: Family Correspondence (1807-1889); Personal Correspondence (1793-1895); Business Correspondence (1814-1923); Business records (1790-1913); Ledgers (1813-1905); Account books (1796-1895); Day books (1901-1912); Saw books (1802-1827); Grindstone books (1810-1819). Other materials include a school English composition, workbook, private school register, accounts of two estates, a will, correspondence from the Humboldt Club and a fire insurance policy.
Series II: Printed materials (undated, 1809-1981) includes printed materials collected by the family, records relating to the town of Canterbury and related items. Types of materials include almanacs, business cards, advertisements, a Norwich newspaper, and pamphlets. Records of the town of Canterbury date from 1809 to 1877 and include notices of town meetings, military exercises, selectmen's' meetings, tax and school district matters. Also included in this series are unidentifiable company records and family correspondence, paint chip samples, photographs of the Smith family home and mill site taken in May 1981, poems, writings and a school work book.
Acquisition Information
The majority of the Smith papers were donated by a descendent of the families circa 1965. Additional Smith family materials were added in 2003 and the Lassell family materials in 2017.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Taxation; Schools; Advertisements; Sawmills; Insurance policies; Selectmen; Poems; Diaries; Connecticut (state); Canterbury (inhabited place); Education; Blueprints (reprographic copies).; Families; Textile industry; Women; Mills and mill-work; Notebooks; Correspondence; Militia; Local taxation; Flour mills; Decedents' estates; Maps (documents); Publications (documents); Photographs; Local government; Administrative records; Financial Records; Smith Family.; Lassell
- Series I: Family Papers, undated, 1774-1923
  Scope and Content Note
  - Allen, Albert
    - Family correspondence, undated, 1871; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box1:1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Allen, Ebenezer
    - Personal correspondence, 1893; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box1:2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bills and receipts, 1897; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box1:3 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Allen, Imogene Smith
    - Family correspondence, 1860-1876; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box1:4 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Family correspondence, undated, 1877-1889; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box1:5 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Personal correspondence, 1882-1890; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box1:6 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Writings, 1863; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box1:7 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Allen, Joseph Robinson
  - Allen, Joseph R., Mrs.
    - Family correspondence, 1867-1879; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box1:8 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Allen, Josephine Smith
    - Family correspondence, undated, 1871-1878; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box1:9 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Baker, Eliza
  - Baker, Hezekiah
    - School workbook, 1820; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box1:10 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Business account records, undated, 1848; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box1:11 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Baker, John and Sarah
  - Ensworth, Horace
  - Ensworth, Lester
  - Jeffrey, Happy Smith
  - Lasell Family documents
  - Lasell, Albert
  - Lincoln, Fanny E.
  - Palmer, Mary A.
    - Private school register, 1887; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box1:12 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Park, Elijah
    - Personal correspondence, 1821; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box1:13 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Smith Family documents (General, unidentified)
  - Smith, Achsah, Mrs.
  - Smith, Ahira
  - Smith, Alice
  - Smith, Eliezer/Eleazer financial and legal records
  - Smith, Eliezer (1737 - 1813)
    - Business records
      - Account book, 1796-1802; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box2:41 (Box 2, Folder 41)
      - Account book, 1798-1803; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box2:42 (Box 2, Folder 42)
      - Account book, 1799-1810; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box2:43 (Box 2, Folder 43)
      - Account book, 1801-1813; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box2:44 (Box 2, Folder 44)
      - Loose papers from account book, 1801-1813; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box2:45 (Box 2, Folder 45)
      - Account book, 1803; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box2:46 (Box 2, Folder 46)
      - Account book, 1806-1812; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box2:47 (Box 2, Folder 47)
      - Saw book, 1802-1803; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box2:48 (Box 2, Folder 48)
      - Grindstone book, 1810-1812; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box2:49 (Box 2, Folder 49)
      - Bills and receipts, 1803-1813; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box3:50 (Box 3, Folder 50)
      - Unidentified records, 1790-1813; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box3:51 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Accounts of Lydia Story estate, 1811-1813; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box3:52 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Smith, Eleazer (? - 1843)
    - Family correspondence, 1819-1832; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box1:14 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Personal correspondence, 1816-1825; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box1:15 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Business records
      - Correspondence, 1814-1831; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box1:16 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Account book, 1810-1830; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/V.1 (Box 9, Volume 1)
      - Loose papers from account book, 1818-1830; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box1:17 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Account book, 1814-1819; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box1:18 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Receipts from account book, 1814-1819; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box1:19 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Unidentified papers from acct. book, 1814-1819; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box1:20 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Account book, 1823-1824; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box1:21 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Loose papers from account book, 1823-1824; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box1:22 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Saw book, 1812-1817; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box1:23 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Saw book, 1820; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box1:24 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - Saw book, 1821-1824; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box1:25 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Saw book, 1826-1827; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box1:26 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - Grindstone book, 1815-1819; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box2:27 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - Bills and receipts, 1814-1827; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box2:28 (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - Unidentified records, 1814-1832; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box2:29 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Accounts of Simeon Park estate, 1812-1814; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box2:30 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Writings, 1822-1844; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box2:31 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Smith, Eleazer (1797 - 1882)
    - Family correspondence, 1882 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Business records
      - Ledger, 1813-1855; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/V.2 (Box 9, Volume 2)
      - Loose papers from ledger, 1813-1855; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box2:33 (Box 2, Folder 33)
      - Ledger/Account book, 1814-1855; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/V.3 (Box 9, Volume 3)
      - Loose papers from ledger/account book, 1814-1855; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box2:34 (Box 2, Folder 34)
      - Ledger, 1844-1859; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/V.4 (Box 9, Volume 4)
      - Account book, 1791-1847; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box2:35 (Box 2, Folder 35)
      - Loose papers from account book, 1791-1847; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box2:36 (Box 2, Folder 36)
      - Receipts and business records, undated; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box2:37 (Box 2, Folder 37)
      - Promissory note, 1871; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box2:38 (Box 2, Folder 38)
      - Advertisements, undated, 1869-1873; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box2:39 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Will, 1882; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box2:40 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Smith, Elipha
    - Family correspondence, 1807; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box3:53 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Personal correspondence, 1819; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box3:54 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Smith, Frank
    - Family correspondence, 1878; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box3:55 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Personal correspondence, undated, 1893-1895; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box3:56 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Business records
      - Correspondence, 1889-1923; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box3:57 (Box 3, Folder 57)
      - Ledger, 1896-1899; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box3:58 (Box 3, Folder 58)
      - Ledger, 1896-1899; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/V:5 (Box 10, Volume 5)
      - Ledger, 1901-1905; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/V:6 (Box 10, Volume 6)
      - Papers from ledger (V.6), 1901-1905; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box3:59 (Box 3, Folder 59)
      - Account book, 1891-1893; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box3:60 (Box 3, Folder 60)
      - Daybook, 1899 April - August; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box3:61 (Box 3, Folder 61)
      - Daybook, 1899 August - 1900 January; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box3:62 (Box 3, Folder 62)
      - Loose papers from daybook, 1899-1900; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box3:63 (Box 3, Folder 63)
      - Daybook, 1900 January - May; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box4: (Box 4, Folder 64)
      - Loose papers from daybook, 1900 January - May; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box4:65 (Box 4, Folder 65)
      - Daybook, 1900 June - October; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box4:66 (Box 4, Folder 66)
      - Daybook, 1900 October - 1901 March; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box4:67 (Box 4, Folder 67)
      - Loose papers from daybook, 1900-1901; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box4:68 (Box 4, Folder 68)
      - Daybook, 1901 March - October; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box4:69 (Box 4, Folder 69)
      - Loose papers from daybook, 1901 March - October; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box4:70 (Box 4, Folder 70)
      - Daybook, 1901 October - 1902 August; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box5:71 (Box 5, Folder 71)
      - Loose papers from daybook, 1901-1902; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box5:72 (Box 5, Folder 72)
      - Daybook, 1902 September - 1903 August; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box5:73 (Box 5, Folder 73)
      - Daybook, 1903 September - 1905 March; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box5:74 (Box 5, Folder 74)
      - Loose papers from daybook, 1903-1905; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box5:75 (Box 5, Folder 75)
      - Daybook, 1905 April - 1907 February; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box5:76 (Box 5, Folder 76)
      - Daybook, 1907 March - 1908 November; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box6:77 (Box 6, Folder 77)
      - Daybook, 1908 November - 1910 October; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box6:78 (Box 6, Folder 78)
      - Daybook, 1910 October - 1912 November; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box6:79 (Box 6, Folder 79)
      - Daybook, 1912 November - 1915 November; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/V:7 (Box 10, Volume 7)
      - Bills and receipts, 1888-1900; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box6:80 (Box 6, Folder 80)
      - Letterhead, business cards, undated; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box6:81 (Box 6, Folder 81)
    - Smith, Mabel (Mrs. Frank), 1924-1925; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box6:82 (Box 6, Folder 82)
    - Humboldt Club Correspondence, undated, 1893-1894; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box6:83 (Box 6, Folder 83)
  - Smith, Lester
    - Personal correspondence, 1865-1895; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box7:84 (Box 7, Folder 84)
    - Business records
      - Correspondence, 1871-1876; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box7:85 (Box 7, Folder 85)
      - Correspondence, 1877-1885; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box7:86 (Box 7, Folder 86)
      - Correspondence, 1886-1895; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box7:87 (Box 7, Folder 87)
      - Account book, 1882-1895; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box7:88 (Box 7, Folder 88)
      - Orders, 1874-1895; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box7:89 (Box 7, Folder 89)
      - Bills and receipts, 1879-1891; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box7:90 (Box 7, Folder 90)
      - Advertisements, undated; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box7:91 (Box 7, Folder 91)
  - Smith, Orrilla
    - Fire insurance, 1871; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box7:92 (Box 7, Folder 92)
  - Smith, Salmon
    - Personal correspondence, undated, 1793, 1823; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box7:93 (Box 7, Folder 93)
    - School workbook, 1813; 1965-0001/SeriesI:FamilyPapers/Box7:94 (Box 7, Folder 94)
- Series II: Printed materials, undated, 1809-1981
  - Almanacs, 1841-1852; 1965-0001/SeriesII:PrintedMaterials/Box7:95 (Box 7, Folder 95)
  - Business cards, undated; 1965-0001/SeriesII:PrintedMaterials/Box7:96 (Box 7, Folder 96)
  - Chase Turbine Manufacturing Company, undated; 1965-0001/SeriesII:PrintedMaterials/Box7:97 (Box 7, Folder 97)
  - G.H. Bushnell & Co., Cider Press, undated; 1965-0001/SeriesII:PrintedMaterials/Box7:98 (Box 7, Folder 98)
  - Globe Bible Publishing Company, 1890-1894; 1965-0001/SeriesII:PrintedMaterials/Box7:99 (Box 7, Folder 99)
  - Norwich newspaper and lithograph, undated, 1889; 1965-0001/SeriesII:PrintedMaterials/Box7:100 (Box 7, Folder 100)
  - Pamphlets, 1862-1892; 1965-0001/SeriesII:PrintedMaterials/Box7:101 (Box 7, Folder 101)
  - Saw mill supplies, 1868-1869; 1965-0001/SeriesII:PrintedMaterials/Box8:102 (Box 8, Folder 102)
  - Saw mill supplies, 1870-1877; 1965-0001/SeriesII:PrintedMaterials/Box8:103 (Box 8, Folder 103)
  - Saw mill supplies, 1882-1888; 1965-0001/SeriesII:PrintedMaterials/Box8:104 (Box 8, Folder 104)
  - Saw mill supplies, 1889-1895; 1965-0001/SeriesII:PrintedMaterials/Box8:105 (Box 8, Folder 105)
  - Saw mill supplies, undated; 1965-0001/SeriesII:PrintedMaterials/Box8:106 (Box 8, Folder 106)
  - Textile company advertisements, undated, 1836-1872; 1965-0001/SeriesII:PrintedMaterials/Box8:107 (Box 8, Folder 107)
  - Unidentified items, undated, 1877, 1882; 1965-0001/SeriesII:PrintedMaterials/Box8:108 (Box 8, Folder 108)
  - Town of Canterbury
    - Town matters, 1809-1877; 1965-0001/SeriesII:PrintedMaterials/Box8:109 (Box 8, Folder 109)
    - Hanover School District, 1811-1820; 1965-0001/SeriesII:PrintedMaterials/Box8:110 (Box 8, Folder 110)
  - Related materials (unidentified)
    - Company records, undated; 1965-0001/SeriesII:PrintedMaterials/Box8:111 (Box 8, Folder 111)
    - Envelopes and stamps, undated; 1965-0001/SeriesII:PrintedMaterials/Box8:112 (Box 8, Folder 112)
    - Family correspondence, 1856-1866; 1965-0001/SeriesII:PrintedMaterials/Box8:113 (Box 8, Folder 113)
    - Paint chip samples, undated; 1965-0001/SeriesII:PrintedMaterials/Box8:114 (Box 8, Folder 114)
    - Photographs of Smith mill site and home, 1981 May; 1965-0001/SeriesII:PrintedMaterials/Box8:115 (Box 8, Folder 115)
    - Poems and writings, undated; 1965-0001/SeriesII:PrintedMaterials/Box8:116 (Box 8, Folder 116)
    - School workbook, undated; 1965-0001/SeriesII:PrintedMaterials/Box8:117 (Box 8, Folder 117)